middleware is a type of software that
provides common services and
capabilities to Applications outside of
what's offered by the original operating
system it acts as a middle layer
middleware between the application
software and the network in this video
we will go over two things one we'll
quickly create a middleware for a fast
API application and then we'll go over a
more advanced way and that example will
be implementing rate limiting based on
the client IP address on each request
all right so here we need to go ahead
and create a middleware now to start
this tutorial I already have my main.py
file already created with a virtual
environment but I need to First do a pip
install for fast API and uvicorn these
are going to be the main dependencies
for us to learn about fast API
middleware now the very first thing we
need to do is just say from Fast API
import fast API our request our random
string and then create our fast API app
we then need to go ahead and create our
middleware now there's really two
different ways we can create a
middleware in fast API there's the aa.
middleware where we can pass in
HTTP which will get called before every
single API endpoint or we can create a
middleware class which is a little bit
more advanced and we're going to be
going over that later on in this video
but first let's go over the easy one
which is just creating an aa. middleware
that takes in HTTP now just so you can
read along with me a function call so
this call next that we're passing in
this will receive the request as a
parameter this function will pass the
request to the corresponding path
operation then it Returns the response
generated by the corresponding path
operation so this is something that
we're going to be passing into to every
single middleware that we create so what
we can do is I'm just going to erase all
of this now and paste in this response
that's equals await with our call next
request so we're passing in the request
that we get and then we have our call
next we're going to create just random
letters join them together and we're
going to be 10 characters long we're
going to print those 10 characters in
our terminal and then we're going to
create a new header for our response
that's equal to those random letters so
for example if we go ahead and just
create a random endpoint that now says
app.get with a slash and we name this
function say hi and we want to return
hello YouTube If we go ahead and run our
application and we go into our
application we can see that it says
hello YouTube now we can see that it's
going to be logging this response header
of X request ID if we go back into our
browser and we go to
slocs we can see that we have our say
high function right here
and when we want to run this application
when this endpoint gets hit before it
calls the business logic it's going to
call the
middleware and we can see that the
response is hello YouTube but we also
now have this x request ID with the 10
random characters inside now this was a
super easy example of how we can create
a middleware and fast API well we're
really doing is just creating a random
header now there's way more advanced
ways we can deal with middleware because
we're going to be dealing with
middleware if you have a frontend
application and you need to use cores or
for trying to do some kind of business
logic before an endpoint is hit but for
our Advanced application or our Advanced
way of learning middlewares we're going
to create a rate limiting application
now rate limiting means you can't call a
specific function or a specific API
input Point more than x amount of times
per minute and this helps protect you
from like a DDOS attacks and other kind
of security concerns now the very first
thing we're going to do to do this is
I'm going to turn off uvicorn after
erasing everything and we're going to
have a couple more Imports so we have
our normal fast API request and response
we have our Starlight middleware base
where we import our base HTTP middleware
we're going to collect the time so we're
going to collect the time that someone
calls our endpoint we're going to
collect their IP address and we're not
going to allow the same IP address to
hit the same endpoint an x amount of
times within a certain amount of time
period so then we're going to add our
default dictionary and then our typing
of dictionary now the very first thing
we are going to do is just create a new
class that is called Advanced middleware
where we're passing in our base HTTP
middleware from our Starlight middleware
base we are instantiating this class by
calling the parent which is base HTTP
middleware and then we're setting up our
rate Limit Records with our default
dictionary of type float now for
Simplicity sake for this application I
want to implement some type of
logging but it's going to be a lot
easier if we just have a async defa log
message and we just print the log to our
terminal instead of setting up like a
real logging system but this will be
able to show exactly the example that we
want to show we then want to create a
dispatch now this dispatch function is
going to take in our request and our
call next which is the same stuff that
we passed into our easy middleware we're
capturing the client IP address by
saying request. client. Host this
captures the real users IP address we
want to track the current time by saying
time.time and then if the current time
minus the self. rate Limit Records of
the client IP is is less than one well
then we want to tell the user the rate
limit has been exceeded and throw a
status code of a
429 now this allows the user to only be
able to call one request per second
after we throw up this guard Clause
let's go ahead and say self. rate Limit
Records over client IP address equals
the current time let's go ahead and just
throw in some logging by saying path
equals request URL path so that's going
to be able to capture the API input
point and then we can log that message
of request to and this is just going to
be probably slash something but it's
going to be able to document the API
endpoint that was tried to be hit we
then want to process the request by
saying start time equals time.time which
our response is going to be equal to our
call next request and then process time
is going to equal our time minus the
start time let's do something similar to
how we did the last middleware where we
created a new header but this time we're
going to create a custom header that
says X process time where we're going to
string our process time that we have up
here and then we're going to say for
header value in custom headers do items
we just want to do a response of our
headers and then appin the header in the
value and then lastly Let's do an
asynchronous logging for our process
time where we're just doing our log
message but remember our log message is
essentially just going to be printing to
our terminal but we're going to be doing
it in asynchronously so it can be like a
background task or something like that
that in the future now one thing we will
have to do is we will have to set up our
app. add middleware and then pass in our
Advanced middleware into our
application now when we do this fast API
is expecting this Advanced middleware to
be ran before every single endpoint so
if we create an easy endpoint that's
just a get request with a slash and we
say message hello world if we go ahead
and do a uicorn main colon app-- reload
and we open up our application as soon
as we can see this we can see that it's
opened by default the request took this
many seconds so extremely fast call and
now if we go ahead and we just refresh
the page and we refresh around like
every 1 second it's going to work and
just keep printing hello
world however if we refresh a whole
bunch of times in a row we're going to
get rate limit exceeded and that's
because we are not not allowing more
than one call per second per API
endpoint all right well this is
everything I wanted to show you for this
video and I will see you in the next